Let's touch our navigation items and adjust them to our new world in which we are now with routing.
Gezinti elerimize dokunun ve onlar rotamzla birlikte bulunduumuz yeni dnyaya ayarlayalm.
So in that navigation items here, here we have our links, our navigation item components where we
Dolaysyla bu snftaki gezinme esinde, balanty nereye aktardmz gezinme esi bileenlerimize
pass the link.
ait linklerimiz var.
Now here I already want to adjust something,
imdi burada bir eyi ayarlamak istiyorum zaten.
we have the burger builder and the path and it should be slash
Burger kurucumuz var ve POF kesinlikle eik izgi olmaldr.
but the second item should lead to /orders and actually have a caption of orders too. Now inside
Ancak ikinci e, eik izgi siparilerine yol amal ve aslnda siparilerin bir balna sahip olmal nk
the navigation item, we also have to adjust something because right now we're using a normal anchor tag.
gezinme esinin de ayarlanmas gerekiyor nk u anda normal bir apa etiketi kullanyoruz.
Now as you learned when using routing I don't really want to do that,
imdi rota kullanrken rendiiniz gibi bunu gerekten yapmak istemiyorum.
instead I want to use the link provided by the react router.
Bunun yerine yeniden ynlendirici ynlendiricinin salad balanty kullanmak istiyorum.
So from react-router-dom, that's the package
Yeniden ynlendirici ynlendirici Domm'den paket pakette.
but now I don't want to use the normal link component, I'll use nav link because I want to style the active
Ancak imdi normal balant bileenini kullanmak istemiyorum nk NAV balantsn kullanyorum, nk aktif balanty stil etmek istiyor
link and actually I want to use the default of having a css class named active because that's the
ve aslnda C adl S snf olduu iin aktif olarak adlandrlm bir C S S snfnn varsaylann
css class
kullanmak istiyorum.
I have defined in my css file too.
Benim C S hatamda da tanmladm.
If you chose a different class name here, you will have to adjust the class name which is assigned by a nav
Burada farkl bir snf ad setiyseniz, ynlendirme modlnde gsterildii gibi bir deniz
link as shown in the routing module.
yolu balantsyla atanan snf adn ayarlamanz gerekir.
Now with nav link imported, I want to use it instead of the anchor tag, ref therefore becomes two and
e aktarlan mantling ile, ref yerine balama etiketi yerine kullanmak istiyorum, bu nedenle iki olur ve
the class name isn't needed at all,
snf ad hi gerekmez.
we don't have to define if it's active or not,
Etkin olup olmadn tanmlamak zorunda deiliz.
it will automatically determine this.
Bunu otomatik olarak belirleyecektir.
Now here the closing tag of course all that should be nav link.
Elbette ki burada kapan etiketi tm Appling olmaldr.
Now since we no longer need to pass the information whether that's active or not, I can go back to the
Artk aktif olup olmamasna bakmakszn bilgileri aktarmamz gerekmediinden, navigasyon esine geri
navigation item and I no longer need to set this active prop here
dnebilir ve artk bu Propp eylemini burada ayarlamam gerekmez.
so let's get rid of that too.
Bu yzden de ondan kurtulalm.
Now let's save all files and go back to our application
imdi tm dosyalar kaydetmek ve uygulamamza geri dnelim.
and as you see, we see the updated navigation items but we don't see an active item.
Grdnz gibi gncellenmi gezinme elerini gryoruz, ancak aktif bir e grmyoruz.
Now let's hover over this item and you'll see that it has the active class,
imdi bu enin zerine gelelim ve aktif snfa sahip olduunu greceksin.
do you know why it's not working?
Neden almadn biliyor musun
This is tricky to spot, but it makes perfect sense that we don't see this class having any effect.
Bu nokta bulmak zor ama bu snfn herhangi bir etkisinin grmediini mkemmel bir mantkl klyor.
It is related to css modules,
Modl olarak grmekle alakaldr.
keep in mind the nav link automatically appends or attaches a class named active.
Balantnn, otomatik olarak aktif adl bir snf ekledii yere eklediini unutmayn.
And of course, we set up the active class here, a navigation item css
Ve elbette burada etkin snf bir gezinti esi C S S. olarak kurduk.
but keep in mind that css modules will actually take our class names here and convert them into unique
Ancak, C S S modllerinin aslnda snf adlarmz burada alp benzersiz snf
class names.
adlarna dntreceini unutmayn.
Therefore when we set up active here in css, it won't come out as active,
Dolaysyla burada S nin C'sinde faaliyete getiimizde faal olarak ortaya kmaz.
it will have some hash attached to it,
Buna biraz karma eklenecek.
it will be unique.
Benzersiz olacak.
Therefore active class attached at runtime by nav link will not match our active class.
Bu nedenle, alma saatlerinde martarak eklenen snfn hareketi aktif snfmza uymaz.
We can easily fix that though, that nav link element has one extra property we can set up,
Naff balant elemannn kurabileceimiz ek zelliklere sahip olmasna ramen bunu kolayca dzeltebiliriz.
we can set our own active class name as you learned.
renirken kendi aktif snf ismini belirleyebiliriz.
You can add active class name here, and here
Aktif snf sonuna kadar buraya ekleyebilirsiniz.
I then want to use classes, active again referring to my classes object which comes from my css file,
Daha sonra, C S S dmden gelen snflarm nesnesine atfta bulunarak tekrar aktif dersler kullanmak isteyecektim.
this will now be the active class name as our css modules transformation spits it out.
C snf dnm tkettiinde, bu artk snf adnn bir kusurudur.
Now with that, if we save this you already see it's now active because actually the class name is Navigation
imdi bunu kaydettiysek, imdi etkinletiini grrsnz, nk aslnda snf ad altndadr
Item__active__some hash, this is our unique class name. We can
ki gezinme esi altizgi altizgi altn iziyor baz karma bizleri de emir zerine tklayabileceimiz
also click on orders now
benzersiz snf adlarn gsteriyor.
and you see we are on orders,
Ve grdnz gibi emir verdik.
it is active but the first link also is still active.
Aktif ama ilk link hala aktif.
Now you probably can fix this,
imdi bunu muhtemelen dzelteceksin.
definitely go ahead and do so
Kesinlikle devam edin ve yapn.
and otherwise I will show you my fix to this in a second.
Ve aksi halde, sana bu fikrini bir saniye iinde gstereceim.
This of course is also active due to the way this nav link interprets the active route.
Bu, elbette, sklmenin etkin rotay yorumlama ekli nedeniyle de aktiftir.
Keep in mind that the to path here is what determines whether this is the active route or not and it's
Unutmayn, burada demek, etkin rota olup olmadn belirleyen eydir ve renirken bir
treated as a prefix as learned.
nek olarak kabul edilmektedir.
So as long as our current paths starts with this path here, this link is treated to be active.
imdiki pauvr'larmz bu blmle baladka, bu balant aktif olarak deerlendirilir.
And for just slash every route starts with that.
Ve sadece eik izgi iin her rota bundan balar.
So we can simply fix this by adding the exact route here
Dolaysyla, bunu tam olarak buradan ekleyerek dzeltebilirsiniz.
and with that we make sure that this only gets used if it is exact.
Ve bununla, eriilirse bunun yalnzca kullanlmasn salyoruz.
Now of course will attach exact to all nav links,
Elbette, tm nav balantlarna eriimi ekleyeceiz.
If you only knew that somewhere this should happen, you could simply pass the exact property, a new property
Yalnzca bunun bir yerde olmas gerektiini biliyorsanz, yalnzca mlke yeni
i just defined to navigation item and in navigation item, you can now bind the exact prop of nav link
bir mlkiyetle geebilir veya navigasyon esine iyi geebilirsiniz ve navigasyon esinde artk
to props exact, so to the one you're passing in from outside.
NAV balantsnn Propp'sunu tam olarak geeceinize balayabilirsiniz. Dardan.
Now this will actually only be used on the first link with just slash and not on the second with orders.
imdi bu aslnda sadece ilk satra sadece eik izgi ile, ikinci srada da emirle kullanlacak.
The result still is the same burger builder is only active if we are on the burger builder, if we are
yalnzca Bergere kaya zerindeysek aktif olur, emirlerimiz varsa emirler aktif olur.
on orders, then the orders are active.
Sonu yine de ayndr Bergere Boulder,
Now this is how we implement the links.
imdi balantlar bu ekilde uyguluyoruz.
Now let's make sure that we actually fetched the orders from the server.
imdi siparileri sunucudan aldmzdan emin olalm.